Guide to the James Schwabacher Collection ARS.0024
Archive of Recorded Sound
James Schwabacher Collection
1860-2006
ARS.0024
Schwabacher, James
71 boxes
Archive of Recorded Sound
The James Schwabacher Collection consists of sound recordings, correspondence, scores, scrapbooks, clippings, programs, teaching material and other papers from San Francisco philanthropist and lyric tenor James Schwabacher.
Access
Open for research; material must be requested at least two business days in advance of intended use. Contact the Archive for assistance.
Source
The James Schwabacher Collection was donated to the Stanford Archive of Recorded Sound by James Schwabacher in 2006.
Scope and Contents
The James Schwabacher Collection consists of sound recordings, correspondence, scores, scrapbooks, photographs, programs, teaching material and other papers from philanthropist and lyric tenor James Schwabacher (1920-2006). A tireless champion of vocal music, Schwabacher was extremely active in the San Francisco Bay area, not only as a performer, but as a teacher, vocal coach, and radio and television host. Perhaps most significantly, Schwabacher founded the Merola Opera Program, an annual workshop for aspiring singers, in 1957, San Francisco Performances in 1980, and the Schwabacher Debut Recital Series in 1983. The Schwabacher name belongs to one of San Francisco's more prestigious families: Schwabacher-Frey was a major West Coast printer and stationer, and Schwabacher and Company was a successful investment banking firm. His grandmother Carrie, who was a Fleishhacker before marriage, was a composer and pianist, and James grew up surrounded by music. Scrapbooks reveal regular attendance at San Francisco Opera performances, long before he made it to the SF Opera stage himself.
After graduating from Cal in 1941, Schwabacher taught briefly at Stanford, where he conducted the Glee Club and sang in the West Coast premiere of Britten's Peter Grimes and alongside Dorothy Warenskjold in her debut in Der Freischütz. In 1948 Schwabacher joined the San Francisco Opera, playing fourteen roles over four seasons. Schwabacher would soon move away from opera, however, and the majority of his years performing were in recitals and oratorios. His singing career is most notable for a twenty-five year run as the Evangelist in The Passions of St. John and Matthew in the Carmel Bach Festival. The collection contains many recordings from these performances, but it also covers the period where Schwabacher was teaching, mentoring and administrating (he was president of the San Francisco Symphony Foundation and a member of their Board of Governors since 1959, and he was also on the board of the San Francisco Opera Foundation). For more biographical information, consult the oral history by Caroline C. Crawford titled "Renaissance Man of Bay Area Music: Tenor, Teacher, Administrator, Impresario: James H. Schwabacher, Jr." (available at http://content.cdlib.org/ark:/13030/kt987006sc).
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged into fifteen series: 1. Awards and honors; 2. Clippings; 3. Correspondence; 4. Media; 5. Merola Opera Program; 6. Misc. papers; 7. Notes and notebooks; 8. Photographs; 9. Posters; 10. Programs; 11. Publicity and biographies; 12. S.F. Symphony and Opera business; 13. Scores; 14. Scrapbooks and binders; 15. Teaching materials.
Related Collections
The Archive of Recorded Sound also holds the Carmel Bach Festival Tape Collection, ARS0025.
Indexing Terms
San Francisco Opera.; San Francisco Symphony Orchestra.; Schwabacher, James; Tenors (Singers)
- 1. Awards and honors (Box 4, Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  San Francisco Conservatory honorary degree 1983; IVI Voice Symposium plaque 2000; 40th and 60th Birthday tributes
- 2. Clippings, 2 boxes (Box 116, Box 2)
  Newspaper clippings and photocopies of reviews, profiles, etc. Includes coverage of Carmel Bach, Ojai and other festivals.
- 3. Correspondence, 1955-2000; 4 boxes (Box 4, Box 96, Box 86, Box 5)
  Almost all incoming. Mix of personal and professional, but mostly personal (holiday and birthday cards, postcards, letters from Sophie Schwabacher). Includes mail from Kurt Adler, Darius Milhaud, Leontyne Pryce, Sandor Salgo, Wallace Berry, Ned Rorem, Blanche Thebom, Elizabeth Schwarzkopf, Ansel Adams, Bidu Sayao, and Leonard Bernstein. Many concerning Merola program, especially its 20th anniversary.
- 4. Media, 45 boxes 451 open reel tapes; 559 audiocassettes; 711 instantanous discs; 66 compact discs; 33 videocassettes
  - Compact discs and CD-Rs, 66 compact discs and CD-Rs (Audio 103)
    Mix of commercially released and unpublished works. Unrelated published discs were added to regular collection. Among the titles retained here: Allen Bond Sings Schwanengesang; The Jewish School/Roslyn Bazak; Traviata/NYC Opera; Goerne/Schneider SF Performances Recital; Songs of Ned Rorem/Susan Graham; Twilight Fancies/Ruth Golden; Tosca Excerpts/Chautauqua Opera; Joseph Merrick dit Elephant Man/Petit firard; Kenneth Goodson Recital and Oratorio Sampler; Robert Breault, Tenor; Elizabeth Anker Recital.
  - Instantaneous discs and custom pressings, 711 instantaneous discs 59 5-7" discs; 550 8-10" discs; 102 10.5-12" discs (Audio 107, Audio 106, Audio 105, Audio 104, Audio 108, Audio 109, Audio 110, Audio 111)
    Discs are in no particular order, although most multi-part sets are in sequence. Original sleeves have been retained when information is written on them. Variety of brands, some locally recorded. Many of the 12" discs are NBC Reference discs originally used in broadcasts. Majority are opera broadcasts, especially from the Metropolitan Opera. A partial list of these discs (dated 1939-1944) is available. There are also many Schwabacher performances and interviews (including one on KBFC from 1948 and several KPFA airchecks), as well as Schwabacher family recordings. Other discs with local interest include recordings of a Stanford-WSC Playoff from 3/14/41, the Tom Coakley Orchestra at the Palace Hotel over NBC on 11/15/34, the St. Francis Orchestra in 1946, and several recordings of Schwabacher's friend Harry Owens, the Hawaiian orchestra leader. Some custom pressings are by MacGregor and Ingram, others are unlabeled microgroove vinyl discs, possibly for teaching use. Other airchecks and recordings, including Bing Crosby (also one custom press), Burns and Allen, Eddie Cantor, and Jack Benny, are actually from Cynthia Schwabacher's donation from 1993-94.
  - James Schwabacher, "If Music Be The Food Of Love... Recital Performances 1952-1967" (Cambria CD 1127), 2002; 3 compact discs (Audio 95)
  - James Schwabacher, "My Life in Music" with tapes of broadcast, 2 audiocassettes (Audio 113)
  - Schwabacher Debut Recitals, 97 items 50 CD-Rs; 47 audiocassettes (Audio 96, Audio 94, Audio 95, Audio 93)
    Recordings of performances from the Schwabacher Debut Recital series on cassette and CD-R, each in a manila envelope with the singer's name and date. A few contain only the program and no recording. There are also two folders of promotional material (programs, brochures, mailers), a folder of reviews, one folder of correspondence, and two folders of miscellaneous SDR material.
  - Tapes, cassette, 559 audiocassettes
    Opera, recitals, demos, interviews, off-air recordings, lectures, classes, copies of commercial releases, etc. Relatively few feature Schwabacher performances.
    - cassettes 1, 228 audiocassettes; 1 DAT (Audio 103, Audio 91, Audio 92, Audio 89, Audio 90, Audio 87, Audio 88)
      Selected titles: San Francisco Opera Gala 11/78; Leontyne Price 4/84; Fromm Lecture 1995; Opera Quiz: Tenors; Singher Inrterview, SFO Pelleas Broadcast 9/79; Piano Practice Tape; Roberto Devereux SFO Broadcast 10/79; Dialogue of the Carmelites SFO 1982; various Met broadcasts; Shere, The Bride; Boy’s Chorus Lunch for Schwabacher; Norskog Town Hall Concert 1980; Johansen Interview; JHS Das Lied ist Aus; Mildred Warenskjold Class 1982; Winther Anderson Memorial Concert 1982; Cantor Joseph Portnoy Musical Reminiscences 1939-1986; Merola Memories; Cenacolo Lectures; Death In Venice Spring Opera Preview 1975; Monte Pederson Recital; KKHI Merola Marathon; A Guide to Pronouncing Medieval and Renaissance French.
    - cassettes 2, 331 audiocassettes (Audio 128, Audio 129, Audio 126, Audio 125, Audio 127, Audio 122, Audio 130, Audio 124, Audio 123)
      Selected titles: Hawaiian Favorites; San Francisco Bach Choir; SF Opera House: Pacific Voices; German Lessons; Berg, Lulu; Marc Coles Recital; Lesson with William Pell; Robert Swenson Radio Interview; answering machine cassettes; Lotte Lehman Farewell Recital 2/16/51; Merola Finals; N.Y. Auditions 1981; Met Finalists 1981; SFOA Finals; Carmel Excerpts 1986; Opening Broadcast, Tribute to KHA, with JHS 1978; Chanticleer Season Highlights 1990-1991; Merola Memories 1991; Hawaiian 78s; James Schwabacher Sings Hawaiian; James Schwabacher, Tales From the Vienna Woods; Merola Auditions; Joseph Ciami Recital; 1993 Adams Fellows; William Corbett-Jones; Saint Ignatius Church Gala Organ Concert; JHS Berlioz, Te Deum; Baroque Arts Ensemble, SF Girls Chorus; Opera Favorites; William Sharp, Baritone; DAT Transfer of JS Disc; Jeff Carney Demo Tape; Jose Garcia (Bass); Polva Frijsh; Didi Boring's Songbook; Bonynge - Schwabacher Interview; Carrie Schwabacher; A Chinese Soprano With A Wobble; JHS KDFC 10/31/85; JHS Salvation Army 1950, Stern Grove 1972; Dorothy Warenskjold, Jan Popper Tribute to JHS, SF Boys Choir Luncheon 4/19/84; Gunnar Johansen; Bing Day, KMPX; JHS TRibute to Otto Guth 11/79; Tekanawa Interview; Alan Farley Speaks About Discography; Margaret Price, J. Reginald DeFoe Interviews; San Francisco Profiles: Jim Schwabacher's SF Opera 10/31/85; Il Mio Tesoro, Schipa, McCormack, Schiotz, Hackett, JHS; JHS Informances - The American Song 3/21/96; Lecture on Wozzeck 11/4/81; SF Opera Intermissions; Men, Women, And Wagnerian Tenors, Complete Broadcast; KKHI Musical Quiz 11/2/90; Opera Preview, Henze Elegy; Tenor, Before and After Lessons; JHS Interviews for Schwab Song Series; Fromm Lectures; SFO Stern Grove; SF Conservatory Of Music 3/20/83; JHS Heather Boy Trial 10/84; SF Opera Gala 1978; My Life In Music 1932-11/86; JHS Sings Poulenc; Ferrugio Interview, Commentary; Marie Louse's 60th Birthday; Conversation with Riegelman; Haugtassa Performance, Mills; James Schwabacher's 60th Birthday
  - Tapes, reel, 451 open reel tapes 2 12" reels; 6 12" reels (1/2 inch tape); 350 7" reels; 91 5" reels; 3 3" reels (Audio 73-85, Audio 131)
    Scope and Contents note
    The majority recordings feature Schwabacher in performance or as host. There are many recitals (some of which are airchecks from stations such as KQED, KPFA, and KEAR), as well as auditions, studio master recordings (on half-inch tape), soundtracks, rehearsals, and previews. Schwabacher was the host of a long-running (1968-1975) program on KKHI titled "Your Symphony: News, Views, Previews" which aired features and interviews with such people as Josef Krips, Seiji Ozawa, Andre Watts, Placido Domingo, the Siegel-Schwall Band (about their collaboration with Ozawa and the SF Symphony), Peggy Salkind, György Ligeti, Yehudi Menuhin, Sandor Salgo, and Oliver Messiaen. There are many tapes from these programs, as well as audio from Schwabacher's 1958 television program on KQED titled "History of Song." The San Francisco Opera and Symphony are well-represented in recordings, and there are also a number of Metropolitan Opera and BBC broadcasts. The tapes are minimally annotated. A compact disc has been released of material from Schwabacher's recitals on tape (Cambria CD-1127, also in the collection).
    A sampling: Opera Jazz Group 1965; Tel Aviv recital 1963; London recital 1967; KPFA recitals 1955, 1957; 1750 Arch recital; audition tapes (many from 1963); SFOA Finals 1982; Carmel Bach Festival; Washington DC recital 1973; Cabrillo Festival KPFA; KQED Meistersinger 1959; Stalingrad; Schumann duets 1963; Lesson with Riegelman 1958, 1960 (also lessons with others); Spring Opera Preview; Metropolitan Opera 1951-1974, etc.; Tristan, Covent Garden 1936; San Bernadino Symphony 1966; Popper, San Francisco Symphony 1960 (and many other SFO); KEAR American Singers, Critics Choice, Opera in English, George Livermore Interview, etc.; Bernstein, Rosenkavalier; KKHI Your Symphony: News, Views, Previews (NVP) 68-75 (JHS host); SF City College Recital 1961; Musgrave, Mary Queen of Scots BBC; Stanford Recital 1961; KEAR Request Program; JHS Recording, Coffing 1970; Vancouver recital 1956; Oakland Museum Concert 1961; Faust intermission, spoken excerpts; Schubert Lieder and Duets SF Chamber Concert 1972; JHS Singing 1953; Carmel Consort Rehearsal; SFO 50th Anniversary, Stern Grove 8/20/72; JHS 40th Birthday Party; Gianni Cigna Dinner Party 1957; Robert Weede Last Recital 9/20/68; JHS Fol De Rol 1958; SF Opera Debut Auditions 1957, 1963; Golden State Recorders recording session 1972; Telemusic Quiz 1973; SFO 25th Anniversary Tosca with Dorothy Kirsten 11/29/70; History of Song 1958; Kiss Me Kate, Hallmark Program (TV) 11/20/58; St. John Passion, New York 1963; KEAR Types of Voices, etc.; SF Conservatory Lieder Recital 1959; Prince Orlovsky Garden Party 1972; Stanford recital 1961; General MacArthur Speech 1951
  - Videocassettes, 33 videocassettes (Box 85, Box 131)
    There do not appear to be many Schwabacher performances on the videotapes. Many are semi-commercial or recorded from television programs. A few highlights: Debut Recital Auditions; Yi-Kwe Sze Memorial Service; Vienna Excerpts 1982-87; Metropolitan Opera; Yehudi Menuhin Conversations; SFO Dangerous Liasons World Premiere 9/10/94; Great Tenors vol. 1-2; Barbara Bonney Symposium on Jenny Lind, Herbst Theatre 2000; Regine Crespin interview; 1982 Anderson Memorial Concert, SFO Adler, Schwabacher; Legendary Singers on TV; SFO Gala 1977; S.V. Symphony 1994; Schwabacher John Callaway Interviews 1982
- 5. Merola Opera Program, 1981-1985; 5 folders (Box 86)
  Applications and evaluations of participants in the annual Merola Opera training program.
- 6. Miscellaneous papers, 9 folder
  - speech draft notebook, radio scripts, Fol De Rol cue sheets, 3 folders (Box 86)
  - UCB Oral History interview transcript [printed and bound 1994], 1986; 1 book (Box 4)
  - Gold Curtain, KEAR. Program Notes and Letters, 1955; 1 folder (Box 113)
    Scripts for Schwabacher's radio program The Gold Curtain on San Francisco station KEAR, along with correspondence from listeners.
  - misc. essays, papers, reports, periodicals, 4 folders (Box 4, Box 116)
- 7. Notes and notebooks, 5 folders (Box 112, Box 5, Box 1)
  Various bound notepads containing notes, song lyrics, travelogues, etc. Two folders of loose notes, clippings, correspondence and other ephemera removed from book collection in boxes 5 and 112.
- 8. Photographs, 2 boxes (Box 86, Box 1)
  Majority are publicity portraits, especially of Schwabacher. Some inscribed portraits of former students. Some snapshots, family photographs (including 1920s-era Fleishhacker family photos), travel pictures (especially from Spain and North Africa, 1981), and an album of a circa-1940s costume party.
- 9. Posters, 5 folders (Folder 137, Folder 135, Folder 136, Folder 133, Folder 134)
- 10. Programs, 5 boxes (Box 116, Box 3, Box 112, Box 4, Box 5)
  Programs, handbills, fliers, press releases, radio and television program guides, etc. Includes programs from Carmel Bach Festival, San Francisco Opera, San Francisco Symphony, etc. A folder in box 4 contains theatre handbills from the 1860s-1880s originally owned by James H. Schwabacher, Sr.
- 11. Publicity and biographies, 3 folders (Box 4, Box 86)
  Brochures, reviews, programs and handbills, N.Y. debut correspondence 1962, etc.
- 12. San Francisco Symphony and Opera business, 2 folders (Box 4, Box 96)
  Correspondence, memoranda, board minutes, etc.
- 13. Scores, annotated and inscribed, 4 boxes (Box 112, Box 138, Box 139, Box 140, Box 6)
  Some are manuscripts or copies. Many are inscribed by their composer to Schwabacher (including works by Francis Poulenc, Gian Carlo Menotti, Charles Boone, Francis Parmentier, Richard Felciano, Harry Owens, Ernst Bacon, Ellis Kohs, Frederick Jacobi, Hans Linne, and Anthony Milner). Others are personally inscribed to Schwabacher's friend Noel Sullivan by Langston Hughes, W.C. Handy, and Ernest Bloch. There is also the sheet music for James' grandmother Carrie Schwabacher's Philomath March.
- 14. Scrapbooks and binders, 35 scrapbooks; 3 binders
  - Music, 1931-1935; 1 scrapbook (Box 7)
    Programs, review clippings, and ticket stubs from the San Francisco Opera, San Francisco Symphony, etc.
  - Plays, Movies, Sports, 1932-1935; 1 scrapbook (Box 7)
    Includes JHS school drama productions
  - Entertainment, 1934-1937; 1 scrapbook (Box 7)
    Mostly newspaper clippings with photographs and biographical profiles of opera stars. Also some (unpublished?) reviews written by JHS.
  - opera scrapbooks, 1936-1937; 2 scrapbooks (Box 7, Box 86)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs, 1946-1948; 1 scrapbook (Box 7)
    Chronicles Schwabacher's activity at Stanford in the late 1940s as an assistant professor in the music department, conductor of the glee club, associate conductor of chorus, and program director for a listening party at the Tressider residence (Music at Home series). Many clippings are from the Stanford Daily.
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 5/40-7/48, 1940-1948; 1 scrapbook (Box 8)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 8/48-11/50, 1948-1950; 1 scrapbook (Box 8)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 9/50-8/51, 1950-1951; 1 scrapbook (Box 8)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 8/51-11/52, 1951-1952; 1 scrapbook (Box 8)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 1/53-6/55, 1953-1955; 1 scrapbook (Box 8)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 7/55-12/56, 1955-1956; 1 scrapbook (Box 8)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 2-10/57, 1957; 1 scrapbook (Box 9)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 11/57-1/59, 1957-1959; 1 scrapbook (Box 9)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 1/59-7/60, 1959-1960; 1 scrapbook (Box 9)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 7/60-5/61, 1960-1961; 1 scrapbook (Box 9)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 5-12/61, 1961; 1 scrapbook (Box 9)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 1-2/62, 1962; 1 scrapbook (Box 9)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 2/62-3/63, 1962-1963; 1 scrapbook (Box 10)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 5/63-6/64, 1963-1964; 1 scrapbook (Box 10)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 6/64-4/65, 1964-1965; 1 scrapbook (Box 10)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 4-10/65, 1965; 1 scrapbook (Box 10)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 10/65-7/66, 1965-1966; 1 scrapbook (Box 10)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 8/66-6/67, 1966-1967; 1 scrapbook (Box 10)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 7-12/67, 1967; 1 scrapbook (Box 11)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 2-12/68, 1968; 1 scrapbook (Box 11)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 1-12/69, 1969; 1 scrapbook (Box 11)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 1/70-11/71, 1970-1971; 1 scrapbook (Box 11)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 1/72-12/73, 1972-1973; 1 scrapbook (Box 11)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 1-9/74, 1 scrapbook (Box 12)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 10/74-3/76, 1974-1976; 1 scrapbook (Box 12)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 4/76-7/78, 1976-1978; 1 scrapbook (Box 12)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 7/78-4/80, 1978-1980; 1 scrapbook (Box 13)
  - Schwabacher clippings and programs 5-8/80, 1980; 1 scrapbook (Box 13)
  - Merola 20th Anniversary, 1982; 1 scrapbook (Box 13)
  - Merola Memorial Fund/The Early Days binder, 1956-1970; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Spring Opera binder, 1960-1964; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Spring Opera Promotions binder, 1978; 1 folder (Box 4)
- 15. Teaching material, 6 boxes (Box 115, Box 114, Box 4, Box 113, Box 86, Box 116)
  Notes, articles, scores, scripts, audiocassettes, etc. Most are in manila envelopes pertaining to a single work. Particular focus on Verdi, Wagner, Mozart, and Strauss. There are also folders on French pronunciation, humor, and the history of opera in San Francisco. Classes include S.F. Girl's Chorus lectures, an Eastman masterclass from 1985, and San Francisco Performances "Informances."